William J. Freburger Papers
University of Notre Dame Archives
William J. Freburger Papers
1963-1993.
FRB
Freburger, William J.
9 linear feet
University of Notre Dame Archives Notre Dame, Indiana 46556
Contractual restrictions may apply.
Mary Freburger, widow of William J. Freburger.
Scope and Content
Mimeographed booklets from his theological studies, 1963-1965: De Ente Supernaturali, De Methodo Theologiae, Activitas Intellectus, Interpretatio Fontium Aetatis Patristicae, all in Latin, the last one with notes in English by Freburger.Manuscripts and mimeographed papers, 1972-1982: William J. Freburger's "Initiation of Infants and Children: a Liturgical Commentary"; "An Analysis and Critique of the Directory for Masses with Children" by James E. Haas; "Adaptation of the Rites of Ordination: Prologomena to the Discussion" by Nathan Mitchell, OSB; "American Catholics and Liturgical Innovation" and "Changing Attitudes of American Catholics toward the Liturgy" by William C. McCready; "Attitudes of Catholics on Religious Education" (NCCB National Catechetical Directory 1976); "Proclamation" periodical by the Liturgical Commission of Baltimore; "Celebration" by the Baltimore Division of Liturgy.William J. Freburger articles 1982-1993; letters 1963-1964 (time of his studies in Rome); Summer Vacation 1963 and Letters from Rome February - June 1966; National Catholic Reporter memos 1992-1993; Christian Initiation of Infants 1985; The People's work: Twenty Years of Liturgical Reform; The Birthday Book; Liturgy Column for Today's Parish 1976-1978; Homilies for Celebration 1976-1978. Also various other documents, correspondence, manuscripts.Also books and pamphlets from his library, including commentaries, theological texts, reference works.
Background
Author of Eucharistic Prayers for Children (1976), Liturgy: Work of the People (1984), and This Is the Word of the Lord (1984), William Freburger served as an editor of National Catholic Reporter and Celebration.
Freburger, William J.; National Catholic Reporter Publishing Co.
Related Material
National Catholic Reporter Publishing Company Records
Twenty-third Publications Collection
- William J. Freburger: Manuscripts, CFRB
- William J. Freburger: Printed Material, PFRB
  - Pastoral Letters of the United States Catholic Bishops / Hugh J. Nolan, Editor, 1984; PFRB 1/01
    - U.S. Bishops' Pastorals - Volume I: 1792-1940, 1984; PFRB 1/01
    - U.S. Bishops' Pastorals - Volume II: 1941-1961, 1984; PFRB 1/01
    - U.S. Bishops' Pastorals - Volume III: 1962-1974, 1984; PFRB 1/01
    - U.S. Bishops' Pastorals - Volume IV: 1975-1983, 1984; PFRB 1/01
  - The RSV Interlinear Greek-English New Testament / Rev. Alfred Marshall, Translator, 1978; PFRB 1/02
  - Biblia Sacra (Vulgatam Clementinam) / R.P. Alberto Colunga, OP, and Dr. Laurentio Turrado, 1959; PFRB 1/03
  - Novum Testamentum (Graece et Latine) / Augustinus Merk, SJ, 1957; PFRB 1/04
  - The Holy Scriptures (According to the Masoretic Text), 1960; PFRB 1/05
    - Masoretic Bible - Volume I: Genesis to II Kings, 1960; PFRB 1/05
    - Masoretic Bible - Volume II: Isaiah to II Chronicles, 1960; PFRB 1/05
  - A Treasury of Quotations on Christian Themes / Carroll E. Simcox, Compiler, 1975; PFRB 1/06
  - The Liber Usualis / Benedictines of Solesmes (ed.), 1961; PFRB 1/07
  - Worship (hymnal), 1986; PFRB 1/08
  - The Christian Centuries: A New History of the Catholic Church, 1978; PFRB 1/09
    - The Christian Centuries - Volume I: The First Six Hundred Years / Jean Danielou and Henri Marrou, 1978; PFRB 1/09
    - The Christian Centuries - Volume II: The Middle Ages / David Knowles and Dimitri Obolensky, 1978; PFRB 1/09
  - After Virtue: A Study in Moral Theory / Alasdair MacIntyre, 1981; PFRB 1/10
  - Contemplative Prayer / Thomas Merton, 1969; PFRB 1/11
  - In The Human Grain: Further Explorations of Contemporary Culture / Walter J. Ong, SJ, 1967; PFRB 1/12
  - Orality and Literacy: The Technologizing of the Word / Walter J. Ong, 1982; PFRB 1/13
  - The Mysticism of The Cloud of Unknowing: A Modern Interpretation / William Johnston, 1967; PFRB 1/14
  - The Counter Reformation: 1559-1610 / Marvin R. O'Connell, 1974; PFRB 1/15
  - Heaven: The Heart's Deepest Longing / Peter J. Kreeft, 1980; PFRB 1/16
  - Bible History: Containing the Most Remarkable Events of the Old and New Testaments / Right Rev. Richard Gilmour, 1936; PFRB 1/17
  - Dictionary of Proper Names and Places in the Bible / O. Odelain and R. Seguineau, Preface by R. Tournay, OP, Translated and Adapted by Matthew J. O'Connell, 1981; PFRB 2/01
  - Christian Words / Nigel Turner, 1981; PFRB 2/02
  - Compendium Grammaticae Linguae Hebraicae Biblicae / Petrus G. Duncker, OP, 1960; PFRB 2/03
  - An Expositionary Dictionary of Biblical Words / W.E. Vine, Merrill F. Unger, and William White, Jr., 1984; PFRB 2/04
  - The Catholic Priest in the United States: Psychological Investigations / Eugene C. Kennedy, MM, Victor J. Heckler, 1971; PFRB 2/05
  - The Catholic Priest in the United States: Historical Investigations / John Tracy Ellis, Editor, 1971; PFRB 2/06
  - The Catholic Priest in the United States: Sociological Investigations / Rev. Andrew M. Greeley, 1971; PFRB 2/07
  - The Liturgy Documents: A Parish Resource / Elizabeth Hoffman, Editor, 1991; PFRB 2/08
  - The Logic of Analogy: An Interpretation of St. Thomas / Ralph M. McInerny, 1961; PFRB 2/09
  - Documents on the Liturgy (1963-1979): Conciliar, Papal, and Curial Texts / International Commission on English in the Liturgy, A Joint Commission of Catholic Bishops' Conferences, 1982; PFRB 2/10
  - Septuaginta / Alfred Rahlfs, Editor, 1962; PFRB 2/11
    - Septuaginta - Volume I, 1962; PFRB 2/11
    - Septuaginta - Volume II: Libri Poetici et Prophetici, 1962; PFRB 2/11
  - Encyclopedia of Theology: The Concise Sacramentum Mundi / Karl Rahner, Editor, 1975; PFRB 2/12
  - Concise Dictionary of Religious Quotations / Compiled by William Neal, 1974; PFRB 2/13
  - The Book of Catholic Quotations / Selected and Edited by John Chapin, 1956; PFRB 2/14
  - The Roman Catholic Church / John L. McKenzie, SJ, 1969; PFRB 3/01
  - Aquinas: God and Action / David B. Burrell, CSC, 1979; PFRB 3/02
  - A Practical Grammar for Classical Hebrew / J. Weingreen, 1959; PFRB 3/03
  - Exercises in Religious Understanding / David B. Burrell, CSC, 1974; PFRB 3/04
  - Why Good People Do Bad Things / Gerard Vanderhaar, 1994; PFRB 3/05
  - Catholic Revivalism: The American Experience 1830-1900 / Jay P. Dolan, 1978; PFRB 3/06
  - A Concise Dictionary of Theology / Gerald O'Collins, SJ, and Edward G. Farrugia, SJ, 1991; PFRB 3/07
  - Science, Religion, and Christianity / Hans Urs Von Balthasar, 1958; PFRB 3/08
  - The Second Session: The Debates and Decrees of Vatican Council II, September 29 to December 4, 1963 / Xavier Rynne, 1964; PFRB 3/09
  - The Third Session: The Debates and Decrees of Vatican Council II, September 14 to November 21, 1964 / Xavier Rynne, 1965; PFRB 3/10
  - The Catholic Tradition: A History of the Development of Doctrine / Jaroslav Pelikan, 1971; PFRB 3/11
    - The Catholic Tradition - Volume 1: The Emergence of the Catholic Tradition (100-600), 1971; PFRB 3/11
    - The Catholic Tradition - Volume 2: The Spirit of Eastern Christendom (600-1700), 1971; PFRB 3/11
    - The Catholic Tradition - Volume 3: The Growth of Medieval Theology (600-1300), 1971; PFRB 3/11
  - Theologiae Moralis Compendium, Vol. II: P. Marcellino Zalba, SJ, 1958; PFRB 3/12
  - A Sense of Life, A Sense of Sin / Eugene Kennedy, 1975; PFRB 3/13
  - The Open Church: Vatican II, Act II / Michael Novak, 1964; PFRB 3/14
  - Belief and Unbelief: A Philosophy of Self-Knowledge / Michael Novak, 1965; PFRB 3/15
  - Degenarate Moderns: Modernity as Rationalized Sexual Misbehavior / E. Michael Jones, 1993; PFRB 3/16
  - Essential Writings in Spirituality and Theology / Charles Williams, 1993; PFRB 3/17
  - Catholic Thinkers in the Clear: Giants of Catholic Thought from Augustine to Rahner / William A. Herr, 1985; PFRB 3/18
  - Lesbian Nuns: Breaking Silence / Edited by Rosemary Curb and Nancy Manahan, 1985; PFRB 3/19
  - Clowning in Rome: Reflections on Solitude, Celibacy, Prayer, and Contemplation / Henri J.M. Nouwen, 1979; PFRB 3/20
  - The Great Apostolic Blunder Machine: A Contemporary Attack Upon Christendom / John R. Fry, 1978; PFRB 3/21
  - To A Dancing God / Sam Keen, 1970; PFRB 3/22
  - The Four Gospels and the Revelation / Richard Lattimore, 1979; PFRB 3/23
  - The Whimsical Christian / Dorothy L. Sayers, 1978; PFRB 3/24
  - The Church and Culture since Vatican II: The Experience of North and Latin America / Edited by Joseph Gremillion, 1985; PFRB 3/25
  - The Hail Mary: A Verbal Icon of Mary / Nicholas Ayo, CSC, 1994; PFRB 3/26
  - In the Spirit, In the Flesh / Eugene C. Kennedy, 1971; PFRB 3/27
  - Hunting The Divine Fox: Images and Mystery in the Christian Faith / Robert Farrar Capon, 1974; PFRB 3/28
  - An Offering of Uncles: The Priesthood of Adam and the Shape of the World / Robert Farrar Capon, 1967; PFRB 3/29
  - Finding Fault / Michael O. Garvey, 1990; PFRB 3/30
  - The Supper of the Lamb / Robert Farrar Capon, 1969; PFRB 3/31
  - Letters from Vatican City: Vatican Council II (First Session) Background and Debates / Xavier Rynne, 1964; PFRB 3/32
  - A Time for Love / Eugene C. Kennedy, MM, 1970; PFRB 4/01
  - Fashion Me A People: Man, Woman, and the Church / Eugene C. Kennedy, MM, 1967; PFRB 4/02
  - The Return to Man: Man and Religion in the Space Age / Eugene C. Kennedy, 1973; PFRB 4/03
  - The Estranged God: Modern Man's Search for Belief / Anthony T. Padovano, 1966; PFRB 4/04
  - Love's Mind: An Essay on Contemplative Life / John S. Dunne, 1993; PFRB 4/05
  - Art and Prudence: Studies in the Thought of Jacques Maritain / Ralph McInerny, 1988; PFRB 4/06
  - Summa Theologiae / St. Thomas Aquinas, 1951; PFRB 4/07
    - Summa Theologiae Vol. I: Prima Pars, 1951; PFRB 4/07
    - Summa Theologiae Vol. II: Prima Secundae, 1951; PFRB 4/07
    - Summa Theologiae Vol. III: Secunda Secundae, 1951; PFRB 4/07
    - Summa Theologiae Vol. IV: Tertia Pars, 1951; PFRB 4/07
    - Summa Theologiae Vol. V: Supplementum Indices, 1951; PFRB 4/07
  - Theologia Moralis Specialis: De Praeceptis / P. Marcellino Zalba, SJ, 1958; PFRB 4/08
  - De Constitutione Christi: Ontologica et Psychologica / Bernardus Lonergan, SJ, 1964; PFRB 4/09
  - Peoples Mass Book / Edited by Nicholas T. Freund, Betty Zins Reiber, Jeanne H. Schmidt, 1984; PFRB 4/10
  - Gather (hymnal), 1988; PFRB 4/11
  - Lead Me, Guide Me: The African American Catholic Hymnal, 1987; PFRB 4/12
  - Oeuvres / Emmanuel Mounier, 1961; PFRB 4/13
    - Mounier Oeuvres - Tome I: 1931-1939, 1961; PFRB 4/13
    - Mounier Oeuvres - Tome II: Traité du Caractère, 1961; PFRB 4/13
    - Mounier Oeuvres - Tome III: 1944-1950, 1961; PFRB 4/13
    - Mounier Oeuvres - Tome IV: Recueils Posthumes Correspondance, 1961; PFRB 4/13
  - Problematic Man / Gabriel Marcel, 1967; PFRB 4/14
  - Péguy: Oeuvres en Prose: 1909-1914 / Charles Péguy, 1961; PFRB 4/15
  - Charles Péguy: A Study in Integrity / Marjorie Villiers, 1965; PFRB 4/16
  - An Illustrated History of the Popes: Saint Peter to John Paul II / Michael Walsh, 1980; PFRB 5/01
  - The Word We Celebrate: Commentary on the Sunday Lectionary, Years A, B, and C / Patricia Datchuck Sanchez, 1989; PFRB 5/02
  - Basic Chesterton / Gilbert Keith Chesterton, 1984; PFRB 5/03
  - Inside the Vatican / Bart McDowell, 1991; PFRB 5/04
  - Rome Reborn: The Vatican Library and Renaissance Culture / Edited by Anthony Grafton, 1993; PFRB 5/05
  - Missale Romanum, 1962; PFRB 5/06
  - Missale Romanum, 1961; PFRB 5/07
  - Lectionary for Masses with Children, 1993; PFRB 5/08
  - The English-Latin Sacramentary, 1966; PFRB 5/09
  - L'Action / Maurice Blondel, 1949; PFRB 6/01
    - Blondel's L'Action - Vol. I: Le Problème des Causes Secondes et le Pur Agir, 1949; PFRB 6/01
    - Blondel's L'Action - Vol. II: L'Action Humaine et les Conditions de son Aboutissement, 1963; PFRB 6/01
  - Action (1893): Essay on a Critique of Life and a Science of Practice / Maurice Blondel, translated by Oliva Blanchette, 1984; PFRB 6/02